Well, I'm going to say this.
We might have saved the best for last.
You know, I had a conversation with this
gentleman earlier.
It was absolutely as powerful if not
more powerful than that, if you can
believe it. And this is a guy that just
doesn't talk the talk. He walked the
walk. He exposed CIA torture. He did
time in prison for it, and he continues
to speak truth to power.
Ex-CIA, John Kiriakou. Thank you so
much.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you, everybody.
Perfect. Thank you. Thanks, everybody. I
I actually had a
a prepared speech, which I normally
don't do. I just wing it.
I figured if I don't know these issues
by now, I'm never going to know them.
So,
but after listening to Congressman
Kucinich,
uh after watching
Senator Johnson yesterday,
I'm I I think I can't uh I can't give
that speech that I intended to.
What I'd like to do is just to stand
here and say, "Yeah, I agree."
That's kind of the end of the story.
I agree.
But I'll But I'll agree by by throwing
in a couple of anecdotes. For those of
you who don't know me, my name is John
Kiriakou. I spent almost 15 years in the
CIA.
Um and then found myself after 9/11 in
in a couple of leadership positions. I
was the chief of counterterrorism
operations for the CIA in Pakistan after
9/11. Led a series of raids that
resulted in the capture of Abu Zubaydah,
whom we wrongly believed was the number
three in Al-Qaeda.
And then went home to become the
executive assistant to the CIA's Deputy
Director for Operations.
A position
in which I got to see literally
everything
that the CIA was doing around the world.
And I can tell you they are lying about
everything.
Everything.
I mean, just on the surface of things,
think about it.
They told us there was no torture
program. Of course there was a torture
program. That was a lie.
They told us that there was no
archipelago of secret prisons around the
world. That was a lie.
They told us that there was no program
of international renditions or
extraordinary renditions where we were
kidnapping people
who had never been charged with a crime
and then sending them to countries that
they had no ties to
so that they could be tortured. That was
a lie.
And then they told us
"There's nothing happening at
Guantanamo. We're just holding people
there to await trial in the appropriate
federal district courts." That was a
lie.
Literally everything they said was a
lie. Now, listen, I will admit to you
I was a true believer for a long time.
Even though I was a third generation
Democrat, liberal Democrat, we don't use
the word liberal anymore, but
progressive Democrat, three generations.
We had a photograph of Franklin
Roosevelt on our TV,
which I still have.
I can't I can't abide by what the
Democratic Party does anymore than I can
abide by what the Republican Party does
because they're all lying to us.
I want to take you back to
the months after the 9/11 attacks.
We had captured Abu Zubaydah
and I was sitting at the foot of his
bed. My orders were to not leave his
bedside. I was tired, very tired, and so
I was afraid I was going to fall asleep.
So, I tore up a sheet and I tied him to
the bed. He was in a coma, but I don't
know. I was thinking maybe the doctor's
al-Qaeda, maybe the nurse is al-Qaeda.
I'm going to fall asleep in the chair
and they're going to make him escape.
So, I tied him up.
And then I woke up
and I noticed that
one of the FBI guys that was in and out
had left Abu Zubaydah's diary
uh next to the bed. So, when I woke up,
I said I said, "What's that?" "Oh,
that's the diary. We We confiscated it
at the safe house." "But it's in
Arabic." He said, "I can't read it." I
said, "Oh, pass it over here. I'll check
it out."
So, I'm looking through the diary
and much of it was innocuous. The The
CIA and the FBI differ on this and have
for 20 23 years. But much of it was
doodles. He was He was a
very talented artist. Uh some of it was
poetry.
He would write letters. He was 27 at the
time. He would write letters to his
14-year-old self saying uh treat our
parents with respect. Don't say terrible
things to that girl down the block. You
know, have respect for your brothers and
sisters, that kind of thing.
But then also in the diary were the
personal cell phone numbers of three
Saudi princes.
And I'm looking at this like, "What in
the world
are these cell phone numbers?"
So,
I called
Islamabad and I said, "Listen,
I'm sitting here in the hospital and I'm
looking at this diary that we
confiscated and I think it's got the
cell phone numbers of three Saudi
princes."
And the analyst that I called said,
"You've got to be kidding me." And I
said, "No."
So, I read him the names and the
I violated all kinds of security issues.
But anyway, I read him the names and the
phone numbers over the phone. He cabled
headquarters. They just said, "Thank
you."
Another couple of months pass.
I go back to CIA headquarters. By then,
this information had bubbled up to the
director, George Tenet.
This was one of only two times I ever
saw George
uh lose his temper.
Uh Prince Bandar bin Sultan al-Saud, who
was the uh the Saudi ambassador to the
United States and the son of then, what
was he? The
minister of whatever, Prince Sultan.
Defense, I think it was.
George had called Prince Bandar into the
office. And George said,
"We have this information that these
three members of your family
are in the personal diary of the number
three man in al-Qaeda."
And he said, "Bandar, I'm telling you
I'm telling you because we're allies.
We're going to start killing people, a
lot of people. And some of them are
going to be named al-Saud."
So, Bandar left the meeting.
And then over the next couple of weeks,
three things happened.
One of the princes had bariatric bypass
surgery.
And he died on the operating room table.
Somehow.
Another prince was killed in a one-car
accident on the Riyadh to Jeddah
highway.
And then the third prince went camping
in the desert like he used to do all the
time and died of thirst.
Of thirst.
Bandar didn't do us any favors by having
his cousins killed. He set us back. But,
that was the plan.
Because
those three princes would have had to
answer questions as to why in the world
their personal cell phone numbers were
in Abu Zubaydah's diary.
And it wasn't just that.
Why was Omar al-Bayoumi
at
President Bush's Crawford Ranch before
9/11
with Crown Prince Abdullah, and then he
excuses himself from the meeting
to go outside and call the hijackers.
Why was that never investigated?
It's because the CIA wouldn't let us
investigate it. The CIA wouldn't let the
9/11 Commission investigate it. What
kind of commission
was the 9/11 Commission if it was not
permitted to interview CIA officers?
Or if it was not permitted to interview
prisoners at Guantanamo?
What did they just fill in the blanks by
making it up?
And it's not just the Saudis that were a
problem for us. The Israelis were at
least as big a problem.
The Saudis aren't so heavy-handed about
it as the Israelis are. And I'll give
you just one example.
When I got back from Pakistan, I was
promoted. And I uh I went up to the
seventh floor to be the assistant to the
Deputy Director, as I said.
On my first day on the job, I was so
excited.
And I went into the Deputy Director's
office, and I I went like this, and I
said, "So,
what are we doing now?"
And he said, "I actually can't tell you.
You have to go up to the or down to the
sixth floor and sign some secrecy
agreements, and then we'll talk." I
said, "Okay."
They were waiting for me in security.
They had six secrecy agreements lined up
on the table.
And I knew the security officer. I said,
I I need to sign these uh secrecy
agreements.
And so, he had them all laid out. I
signed each and every one. And a secrecy
agreement is such that you promise to
never ever talk about this ever for the
rest of your life. You take it to the
grave unless it's declassified.
And for the most part, it's been
declassified. So,
I signed the six agreements and I said,
"So, what's up?"
And he goes like this.
"Next year,
we're going to invade Iraq.
We're going to overthrow Saddam Hussein.
And we're going to open the biggest Air
Force base in the world
so we can move all of our air assets out
of Saudi Arabia
and deprive Osama bin Laden of the
ability to say that we are polluting the
land of the two holy mosques." I was
dumbfounded. I've just gotten back from
Pakistan where we've all dedicated our
lives to finding Osama bin Laden.
And all I could think to say was, "We
haven't caught bin Laden yet.
What do you mean we're going to
overthrow Saddam Hussein?"
And he said,
"Stop.
The decision's been made.
We don't have a say.
And the battle lines have been drawn." I
said, "What are the battle lines?"
He said, "The pro-invasion forces are
OVP, the Office of the Vice President,
OSD, the Office of the Secretary of
Defense,
and
the National Security Council." And he
said, "The anti-Iraq war factions, as
crazy as this sounds, CIA,
the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
and the State Department."
And I said, "So, what do we do?" He
said, "We do as we're ordered to do.
We're going to go to war with Iraq."
So, that's what we prepared for from
March of 2002 to February of 2003, it
was all about getting ready to fight the
Iraqis. And for what reason? There was
no reason.
I never encountered a CIA officer who
ever believed that there was a
connection between Saddam Hussein and
Al-Qaeda.
Osama bin Laden hated Saddam Hussein as
much as he hated us.
There was literally nothing Muslim about
Saddam Hussein. There was a famous story
that Saddam and his vice president,
Izzat Ibrahim al-Douri, went to Mecca to
make the minor pilgrimage, the Umrah, in
1988 or '89. Saddam didn't know the
prayers
because he had never he had never
learned the prayers.
Izzat Ibrahim was very religious and was
kneeling behind him
and whispering the prayers quietly to
Saddam so Saddam could say them more
loudly to make it look like he knew what
the hell he was doing.
There was nothing Muslim about Saddam
Hussein.
But Dick Cheney said there's a
connection between Al-Qaeda and Iraq,
and that's the reason why we're going to
attack. It was just completely made up.
Just like the weapons of mass
destruction.
Saddam had two sons-in-law, Hussein
Kamel al-Majid and Saddam Kamel
al-Majid. They were brothers married to
Saddam's two daughters, Rana and Raghad.
Raghad and Rana. Raghad was the older
older one.
They defected to Jordan.
And they did it in the middle of the
night because they were panicked that
Saddam's eldest son, Uday, was going to
kill them.
So, we put a team together. We flew out
to Amman, where they had been given
refuge.
And uh
we had this plan that we were going to
go in and say, "All right,
tell us where the weapons of mass
destruction are because we couldn't find
them."
We figured maybe these guys, you know,
have are they're geniuses or something.
They found this one patch of dirt that
our overhead imagery can't find and
maybe, you know, we just missed them or
something cuz none of us ever saw any
weapons of mass destruction.
So, we go to uh to the palace where King
Hussein had them hold up.
And when we walked in,
even before my boss could say anything,
Hussein Kamel said, "All right, I need
overhead uh imagery of Saddam's palaces.
I need air cover. I need secure
communications. I need weapons." And my
boss said, "Oh, wait a minute.
We didn't come here to make you
president of Iraq.
We came here for you to tell us where
the weapons of mass destruction are."
He said, "There are no weapons of mass
destruction."
The truth is, we had so scared the
out of them in 1989 that they destroyed
all the weapons of mass destruction and
they buried the the the ruined missiles
uh in the in the desert.
There were no weapons of mass
destruction. That's why the United
Nations never found any. That's why we
never found any. No country ever Even
the Israelis, they have weapons of mass
destruction. Okay, show us where. We'll
go get them.
And then we'll we'll punish them and
bomb them or something. We're supposed
to take the Israelis' words for it.
So, there were none. In the end, we gave
Hussein Kamel and Saddam Kamel nothing.
Uh they stayed in exile about 6 months
and then they sent word back to
Iraq that they wanted to uh beg
forgiveness and go back.
Uh they were met at the Iraqi-Jordanian
border by Saddam's two sons who executed
both of them.
So, that was the end of it. They never
even made it a foot inside Iraq. Now,
fast forward a little bit more
to the week before we crossed the border
into Iraq. I want to tell you two things
about that.
Number one,
my primary
role
in the Deputy Director's office was to
be the morning briefer
for
all of the Deputy Directors and the
Associate Deputy Directors as well as
the heads of counterterrorism,
counternarcotics, counterproliferation,
counterintelligence, and the chief of
staff. That was at 7:00, and then at
7:30 I would brief the Director.
So, I went into the briefing this
morning and I said, "Before I get into
the substantive reporting from
overnight, we had a message from the
Israelis and they said that they want to
be in on the on the attack
in 3 days."
And the Deputy Director said,
"Absolutely, positively not." And I
said, "I already told them no."
Well, it just so happened
that in the western Iraqi desert
when the Iraqis electrified that part of
the country,
they built electrical towers
with three legs.
And 2 days before we attacked Iraq,
somebody
put explosives on one of the legs for
like 100 miles
and every tower just started tipping
over.
And I remember the Deputy Director
saying, "Those Israelis. They
just don't know when to take no for an
answer. Excuse my language."
So, they got a little piece of the
action.
But, it was the Israelis the whole time
that were that were telling
Well, they were telling the Vice
President's office, it was like an echo
chamber,
"You got to overthrow Saddam." And
Cheney's office would say, yes, we have
to overthrow Saddam. And the Israelis
would say,
They're an existential threat. And
Cheney would say, yes, they are. We're
going to overthrow Saddam. And if the
CIA were like, is nobody paying any
attention to Iran? Saddam Hussein,
whether you like his politics or not,
he's the only thing protecting the Gulf
Arab countries
from Iran.
Once he's gone, that's it.
They they're done if the Iranians
uh decide to do anything about it. The
Israelis didn't care because the
Israelis had a longer view than we did.
The Israeli view was,
we're going to help you take out Iraq.
And then once it's taken out, we're
going to help you take out Iran and
Libya and Syria and, you know,
everybody.
I mean, that was the plan all along.
I mean, look what they did
Look what they did in
Lebanon.
You don't have to like Hassan Nasrallah
at all
or what he stands for or his politics or
whatever
to acknowledge that
what Israel did in Lebanon was a war
crime.
But they don't care about that.
They'll kill This is This is one thing
that they do that most other countries
in the region don't do as a matter of
policy.
If they have a target located in a
in a
block of apartments, let's say, they
will blow up the entire city block and
kill a thousand people if they think
they can get that one guy.
That one. Nobody else does that.
And then they bombed Qatar last week.
Did everybody in the world forget that
it's Qatar that's the home to the
largest US air base in the world?
And the Qataris finally today came to us
and said, so what are you guys going to
do about this?
They bombed us in broad daylight
knowing we're US ally
knowing that
we have the largest American airbase in
the world here
and you guys just said, "Oh, well, you
know what? They didn't inform us."
So, sorry.
With our own weapons, thank you.
With our own weapons.
We put up with
things from the Israelis that are
incomprehensible to anybody who follows
these issues.
It It's just It's an utter mystery to me
why we tolerate this kind of of behavior
from anybody. We wouldn't tolerate this
from from an enemy, certainly.
Why would we tolerate it from a friend?
And, you know, I'm going to use friend
in air quotes. Forgive me if you've
heard me tell these stories.
But, I was on the job for, I don't know,
3 months, maybe. This was in early 1990,
like March of 1990. And, I was
instructed to attend my very first
liaison briefing. This is the first
briefing I ever did as a young
25-year-old, 20 whatever I was,
24-year-old CIA officer.
We're going to brief the Israelis. And,
I said, "Okay. It's going to be the
first foreign intelligence service that
I'm declared to, where they say, 'This
is John Kiriakou. He's a CIA officer.
He's going to brief you today.'"
So, the first thing I was told was
"We're not going to brief them here at
headquarters." I said, "Oh, okay. Why
not?"
"The Israelis aren't allowed to come in
headquarters."
I said, "Why not?"
"Because every time they come, they
bring us gifts, and the gifts always
have listening devices embedded in
them."
Every time. And, they're packed with
batteries. Like, they'll give We have a
seal of the CIA. We want to give it to
you as a gift. Well, we have seals
everywhere in every room. And, this
one's packed with batteries that will
last for 18 months. So, no, we're not We
don't want your gift. Thank you.
So, we meet them in
an off-
campus
place. We We call it this the Israel
safe house, okay?
So, I'm the junior most analyst
at this briefing,
which meant that I went last. So,
everybody else went first. There were
like 11 of us. The political analyst,
the economic analyst, the military
analyst, the oil analyst, the overhead
imagery lady came over from the Navy
Yard, and everybody did their thing. I
was the
um Iraq uh leadership analyst, which
meant I
What I did all day was to do
psychological profiles of the Iraqi
leadership.
So, it comes to me, and I was given the
script to follow, and I said, "Hello, my
name is John Kiriakou. I'm the Iraq
analyst in the Office of Leadership
Analysis."
And there were two Israelis in the
briefing, one Mossad and one Shin Bet.
And the Shin Bet guy writes down my
name, and he says, "Spell your name."
So, I spell it for him. And then he
looks up at me over his glasses, and he
says,
"You are
Jewish?"
And I said, "I am not recruitable.
Don't even think that you can recruit
me."
I was so angry, I was shaking as I gave
the briefing, and I said, "Now I have to
go to security and report that I was
pitched."
And they laughed, and they said,
"They've done that to all of us.
It's like they can't help themselves."
I was furious. My boss, when I got a
home When I got back to the office, my
boss said, "How did it go?" I said, "I
want to strangle that Shin Bet guy."
And he said, "I knew it. I knew he was
going to pitch you. He pitches all of
us."
Well, the head of security at the CIA
added a little something.
In a briefing
in which we were being warned about
counterintelligence
threats, we were told to never ever ever
go to this steakhouse on Route 123 that
is closest it's the closest restaurant
to the CIA. And the reason why we're not
allowed to we were not allowed to go
there is because the Russians thought
that that's like the only place we went.
So, anytime you go, it's all KGB agents
sitting together waiting for the CIA
people to go in and they never went in.
We would always go another mile down the
road and go to other restaurants.
So, um
as part of that briefing, he said, "You
know, it's not just the Russians we have
to worry about." He said, "Israel is
ranked as critical threat, the highest
threat level, critical threat for
counterintelligence."
He said, "Many of you have met the
Mossad and Shin Bet representatives at
the Israeli Embassy here." I had just
met them.
And he said, "Well,
there are 189
undeclared Israeli spies fanned out all
across the United States to steal our
defense secrets."
Now, why? We give them everything.
So, why would they be spying on us?
Actually, cuz we don't give them
everything. We give them only 99% of
everything.
And they want that last 1%. I'll give
you an example.
When we developed the F-35,
we said to the Israelis, "Hey, we're we
have this new thing, this new F-35. It's
supposed to be our best plane. It's
stealth and it's a bomber and it does
all kinds of great tricks." They said,
"We want it."
We said, "Yes, that's why we're offering
it to you. We're going to give you the
first F-35. We're going to call it the
F-35I for Israel."
And they said, uh
"Why are you going to make a difference
between the F-35 and the F-35I?" And we
said, "Because, God forbid, if you're in
a dog fight or there's a mechanical
malfunction and it crashes, we don't
want the Iranians to get it, the
Russians, the Chinese, the Syrians. So,
what we're going to do is we're going to
very slightly degrade the avionics."
Well, they didn't like that one bit.
And so, they decided to steal the
avionics.
At the same time, the Emirates came to
us and they said, "Hey, we want this
F-35." We said, "Great, we're going to
give it to you. We're going to call it
the F-35E
for Emirates. It's going to be exactly
the same as the F-35I. So, we're going
to slightly degrade the avionics." They
said, "Fine, we'll take it."
Not the Israelis.
They wanted the F-35, period.
With no letter afterwards.
A couple of years later, I decided I
wanted to serve overseas.
And um
several of my colleagues in the office
also wanted to serve overseas at the
same time in what was called the analyst
overseas program. You'd do a
rotation, an actual transfer to the
State Department and you serve as a
foreign service officer.
And so, I went to Bahrain. My friends
actually got married and went together
to Jerusalem.
So, when they arrived
the ambassador took them to Mossad and
said, "You already know my officers.
They've gotten married and they're here
declared to you. The wife is going to
work on Palestinian political issues and
the husband is going to go to the
university and learn Arabic."
And they said, "Fine."
So, the ambassador held a welcome party.
They call They call it a hail and
farewell party. You say, "Hello, welcome
to the new people." and farewell to the
people who are transferring out.
And when they um
got back home from Tel Aviv later that
night
they saw that all of their living room
furniture had been rearranged
while they were gone. And they're like,
okay, going to be jerks about it. So,
they reported it and
and the embassy said, yeah, they do
that. They'll break into the house and
just just so that you know that they can
do whatever they want. You There's
nothing you can do about it.
A year later,
they go to another party at the at the
ambassador's residence and when they get
home,
people had
taken shits in all of the toilets in
their house
and left them unflushed.
So, they're like, all right, Israelis
again. They have to report it. They
broke into the house. They took a dump
in the house so all every one of the
toilets. And they give us these giant
houses, right? Cuz you're you have to
entertain. So, like for me, my wife and
I had our son was like 16 months old. I
had like a five-bedroom house. Talking
about big houses
with lots of toilets.
Another year later,
it's time to leave and to come back to
headquarters and so the ambassador
throws a
hail and farewell party for them.
And then they get back to the house
and the dog is under the dining room
table and he's whimpering
because they had cut his tail off
and they wrapped it in gauze and medical
tape.
Why?
You're supposed to be our best friends
in the world. Why would they do
something like this?
It's because they're not our friends.
They care only about themselves,
quite literally.
And if it means spying on us
and stealing our secrets and harassing
our employees and lying,
maybe maybe killing Americans?
You know?
I was going to I was going to say I
apologize I only have 2 minutes left,
but I was going to say something in my
original planned speech about the
dancing Israelis. Of course they were
dancing.
You bet they were dancing because they
knew exactly what 9/11 meant. 9/11 meant
that we were going to feel compelled to
go overseas and kill as many Muslims as
we possibly could. Of course they were
dancing in the streets. That's exactly
what they wanted to happen.
Exactly what they wanted to happen. And
it's what happened. But then when it
wasn't good enough for us to go kill
Afghans
or a handful of Al-Qaeda people
they engineered Iraq
with Dick Cheney and David Addington and
Scooter Libby and all of the other war
criminals who were working either at the
White House or at the Pentagon at the
time.
And now here we are all these years
later, we still don't know the truth
about 9/11.
We don't know the role that the Israelis
played. We don't know the role that the
Saudis played because we're not allowed
to investigate it.
And uh we're supposed to just uh
just shake the Israelis' hands and
forget about all the past and wish them
the best or else you're an anti-Semite.
Remember?
If you're anti-Netanyahu, by God that
means you hate all Jews and we can't
have that.
And so here we are 24 years after the
fact. You know, in my mind 9/11 was like
last Tuesday.
Um
but 24 years have passed.
And we're no better off than we were 24
years ago.
Not while we have or worse.
Not while we have the Israelis hanging
around our necks like an anvil.
So thank you very much for listening to
me.
>> [applause]